Finding Aid for the Lynn Townsend White papers, 1937-1985 LSC.1541
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lynn Townsend White papers
1937-1985
UCLA Library Special Collections
White, Lynn Townsend, 1907-
LSC.1541
9 oversize_boxes
Lynn Townsend White, Jr. (1907- ) was a professor of history at UCLA (1958-72), and Director of the UCLA Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies (1964-70). The collection consists of teaching and research material related to Lynn White's career as a history professor.
Restrictions on Access
Stored off-site. All requests to access special collections material must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Maude White, 1987.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942339893606533
Biography
Lynn Townsend White, Jr. was born in San Francisco, California, April 29, 1907; BA, Stanford University (1928), MA, Union Theological Seminary (1929), Harvard University (1930), Ph.D, Harvard University (1934); history instructor, Princeton University (1933-37); assistant professor (1937-40) and professor (1940-43) of history at Stanford University; President, Mills College (1943-58); professor of history, UCLA (1958-72); Director of the UCLA Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies (1964-70); recipient of numerous honorary degrees, awards and decorations; various publications include: Educating our daughters: a challenge to the colleges (1950), Frontiers of knowledge in the study of man (1956), Medieval technology and social change (1962), Medieval religion and technology (1978).
Scope and Content
Collection consists of teaching and research material related to the career of history professor Lynn White. Includes exams, lecture notes, publications, correspondence, manuscripts, bibliographic files, and photographs for publications.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Teaching materials (Boxes 1-4).
Research materials and publications (Boxes 5-11).
Correspondence files (Boxes 12-15).
Bibliographical files (Boxes 16-22).
Photographs used in Lynn White's publications (Boxes 23-24).
Related Material
Technology, History, Democracy [oral history transcript] / Lynn Townsend White, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1983. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
College teachers -- California -- Archives.; Historians -- California -- Archives.; History teachers -- California -- Archives.; White, Lynn Townsend, 1907- --Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of History--Faculty -- Archives
- Teaching Materials
  - Exams
    - History 100, 1937-1942. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - History 121A, 1962-66, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - History 121E, 1960-1972. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - History 124, 1959-1961. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medieval History
    - M.A. Examinations, 1959-1970. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Ph.D. Examinations, 1959-1970. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lecture Notes
    - History 11, 1940-43, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - History 100, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - History 101, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - History 101, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - History 121A [v.1], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - History 121A [v.2], n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - History 121B, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - History 124, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - History 139, 1942. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - History 140, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - History 253AB, 1973-74, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - History 254A, 1967-68. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - History 314, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Humanities III, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Reading Lists
    - History 121A, 1971. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - History 121B, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - History 253AB, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - History 254AB, 1960. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Research Materials and Publications
  - Action Curves and Clockwork Geniuses (article by C. Marchetti): reprint, 1984. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Agricultural Innovation in the Early Islamic World (article by A. Watson) - Review by Professor White, 1984. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Anthropogenic Ecosystem and Soil Biodynamics (article by F.W. Pauli) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Appeal from the Consumer, 1984. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - L'ascendant technologique de 1'Occident Medievale (article by P. Ashtor), 1983. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bagnara, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents note
    Notes.
  - Basilian Houses of Sicily, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Manuscript.
  - Beyond the Ordinary Dimension, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Offprint.
  - British Brodcasting Corporation/Courses by Newspaper, 1977-1980. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Notes and correspondence concerning courses on technology.
  - Canons Regular in Norman Sicily, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Handwritten draft.
  - The Changing Middle Ages, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Typewritten draft.
  - Christians and Nature - article in Pacific Theological Review, 1975. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Day the Universe Changed (TV Series), 1985. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Program summaries.
  - Dead Manuscripts, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Differing Attitudes Toward Technological Innovation in Ancient Rome, Islam, Byzantium, and the Medieval West, 1985. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Drafts and correspondence.
  - The Diffusion of the Lateen Sail, 1973-1974. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Manuscript, typescript and correspondence.
  - Diffusion vs. Independent Invention ... (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - The Early History of the Cam, 1960-1964, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Manuscript, notes, correspondence.
  - The Ecology of Our Science, 1979. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Critiques, page-proofs and correspondence.
  - The Economic History of Europe (Book to which Professor White was a contributor), 1969-1971. (Box 5, Folder 20)
    Proofs and correspondence.
  - Education at the End of the Occident, 1958. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Typescript and correspondence.
  - Elixir Vitae, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Embryology of Columbus' Discovery, 1976. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Reprint.
  - Energy and the Way We Live, 1979. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Essays in Honor of Lynn White. Jr., 1975. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    (Book which was co-authored by two of Professor White's students)
    Abstracts of articles and correspondence.
  - The Eurasian Context of Medieval Europe, 1979-1981. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Drafts and reprint.
  - The Excitement of Thinking, 1956. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Typed drafts and correspondence.
  - The Expansion of Technology, 500-1500, 1969. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Copy of pamphlet.
  - The Feel of the Road, 1959. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Drafts of commencement address given at Bakersfield College.
  - The Flower of Early Renaissance Technology, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Food and History, 1976. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    Typed drafts, notes.
  - Further Essays on Medieval Technology and Science (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Giovanni Portinari ..., 1965-1975. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Notes, drafts and correspondence.
  - Greek Documents in Bibl. Com. Palermo [word illegible] H 237, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - History and Horseshoe Nails, 1970. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - The History of Mathematics from Antiquity to the Present - (J. Dauben), 1985. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - How Do We Get Original Ideas?, 1959. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Handwritten draft and notes.
  - The Iconography of Temperance, 1966-1968. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Typed drafts; photos (24); negatives (7).
  - Indic Elements in the Iconography of Petrarch's Trionfo della Morte, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Reprint and correspondence.
  - The Inventor of the Crankshaft: Guido da Vigevano, 1982. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Typed draft.
  - Jacopo Aconcio, 1961-1965. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Notes and correspondence.
  - The Legacy of the Middle Ages in the American Wild West, 1964. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - The Liberation of Nature: Lynn White's Challenge Anew (article by H. Paul Santmire). (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Machina ex Deo, 1969-1974. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Correspondence with publisher and translator.
  - Manuscripts - Tentative, v.d.
    - The California Mentality, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Faculty Attitudes ..., 1967. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - The Mood of the Good Life, 1964. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Reflections on Urbanization ..., n.d. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Religion and the Disciplined Mind, 1961. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Religion and Technology, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Two Shapers of World Views, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Medicine and History of Exploration of Matter, 1956. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Draft of speech.
  - Medieval Borrowings from Further Asia, 1971. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - The Medieval Castle: Romance and Reality, Photocopy. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Chapter written by Bernard S. Bachrach (one of Professor White's students).
  - Medieval Europe Foresaw Planes, Cars, Submarines, 1978. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Draft of article for Scientific American.
    Also, correspondence.
  - Medieval Meeting of East and West, 1972. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Copy of article.
  - Medieval Religion and Technology, 1977-1982. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    Draft of introduction and correspondence.
  - Medieval Technology and Social Change, 1956-1960. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Notes for chapters 1 and 3.
  - Medieval Technology and Social Change, 1947-1950. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Notes for chapter 2.
  - Medieval Technology: Transfers and Spinoffs, 1984. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Medieval Uses of Air - Article in Scientific American, 1970. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - On Time and Crime (article by C. Marcetti), 1985. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - The Origins of the Coach, 1970. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Draft and correspondence.
  - The Pattern of Medieval Christianity, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Pietro Rambulo da Messina, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Notes and bibliography.
  - Pietro Ransano, 1984. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Bibliography and correspondence.
  - The Quest for Uncertainty, 1954. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Drafts of speech given at the University of Illinois.
  - Religion and Culture in Our Time (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Drafts of chapters.
  - Rethinking Science for a Rethought World, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Reticences of the Middle Ages, 1970. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Review of J. Needham's Science and Traditional China, 1983. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Richard Lectures, University of Virginia, 1957. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    (These lectures were published in 1962 under the title Medieval Technology and Social Change)
    Correspondence.
  - Science and a Sense of Self, 1978. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Sources for the History of Technology, 1961-1967. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Stanford University Alumni Association, 1978. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Itineraries for travel/study program in Guatamala.
  - Technological Assesment ..., 1974. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Correspondence and reprint.
  - Technological Development in the Transition ..., 1979-1980. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Drafts.
  - Technology - article in Dictionary of the Middle Ages, 1981. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Technology and the Future of Compassion, 1978. (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, reprint.
  - Theophilus Presbyter and Rupert of Deutz ... (article by J. Van Engen), 1980. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Three Biblical Songs [poems by Lynn White], 1956. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Tools and Civilization, 1975. (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Correspondence, corrected copy.
  - The Transformation of the Roman World: Gibbon's Problem After Two Centuries, 1965-1973. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Correspondence, reviews.
  - Tribal Space, Civic Space and the Megalopolis - copy of article by Frank J. Frost (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Two Past Energy Crunches, 1980. (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Draft.
  - Two Sicilian Rescripts, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Viator (Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies journal) - review by R.H. Robbins, 1979. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Notes for unidentified projects. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Bibliography, 1957-71, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Yearly lists of Professor White's publications, lectures, courses taught, etc.
  - Reports of Professor White on manuscripts submitted for publication, 1971-1983. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Vita - Lynn White, Jr. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Research Letters
    - 1951-1958. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1959-1970. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1971-1985. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Correspondence Files
  - Academie internationale d'Histoire des Sciences, 1963-1978. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1971-1979. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1975. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1970. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1968-1971. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Bernard Bachrach, 1971-1980. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - California Council for Humanities in Public Policy, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Committee on Public Ceremonies, 1984-1985. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Conference on pornography and obscenity, 1971-1972. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Copyright, 1976-1978. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Emeriti Association, UCLA, 1977. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Honors Committee, 1974. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Research Lectureship Committee, 1984. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Foreign Contacts, 1962-1980. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Friends of the Graphic Arts, UCLA, 1975. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Future Publications, 1970-1983. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Bruce Gelsinger, 1985. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Haverford College, 1985. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - History of Science Society, 1980-1982. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - India Trip, 1980. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Mautner Memorial Lectures Committee, 1984. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Medieval Academy of America, 1963-1979. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Medieval Academy of America, 1980-1985. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - National Humanities Center, 1977. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Newcomb Award Selection Committee, 1983. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Ordine al Merito della Repubblica, 1971. (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1980-1981. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Publishers (invitations to write), 1959-1971. (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Research Projects
    - 1969-1970. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1971-1976. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1978-1985. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Royal Society of Arts, 1963. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Society for the History of Discovery, 1971. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Society for the History of Technology, 1962-1983. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Society for Italian Historical Studies, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - UCLA Administration, 1957-1982. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - University Professorship, 1980. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1974. (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Fellowship Data, 1978-1984. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Letters of Recommendation
    - (Faculty), 1971-1973. (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - (Faculty), 1974-1977. (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - (Faculty), 1978-1984. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - (Graduate Students), 1964-1972. (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - (Graduate Students), 1973-1977. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - (Graduate Students), 1978-1985. (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Bibliographical Files
  General note
  [Boxes 16-22 are card index boxes]
  - Bibliographies - general, n.d. (Box 16, Box 17)
  - Bibliographies - general: arranged alphabetically and by subject (Box 18)
  - Bibliographies - general: arranged by subject, n.d. (Box 19, Box 20)
  - Bibliographies for book, Medieval Technology and Social Change (Box 21, Box 22)
- Photographs Used in Lynn White's Publications
  - British Museum Horleian manuscript. 328 leaves fol. 48v, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Photos used in book, Essays in Medieval Religion and Technology (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Guillotine, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Photos used in article Indic Influences on the Iconography of Petrarch's `Trionfo della Morta' (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Leiden manuscript Pereizone[?] f.17, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Photos used in book, Medieval Technology and Social Change (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Norman building in Cambridgeshire, England., 1979, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Orvieto Facade, n.d. (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Petrore Pictures (guillotine, gypsies, f-shaped belt drive), n.d. (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Scientific American article photos, 1970. (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Smithsonian Book of Invention, 1979. (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Unidentified, n.d.. (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Oversize photo - unidentified. (Box 24)
- Celebration for Walter Horn and Ernest Born, May 8, 1980. (Box 24)
- The hardware of mathematics. (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Photocopied articles. (Box 25, Folder 2-4)
- Research notes. (Box 25, Folder 5)
- Buffaloes and death - Correspondence and research material. (Box 25, Folder 6)
- Medical astrologers - Correspondence and research material. (Box 25, Folder 7)
- Deutschen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Berlin. (Box 25, Folder 8)
- The medieval English longbow: characteristics and origin. (Box 25, Folder 9)
- International Academy of the History of Science. (Box 25, Folder 10)
- Society for the History of Discoveries. (Box 25, Folder 11)
- Sons of Toil - Bohemian Club. (Box 25, Folder 12)
- Correspondence
  - 1950s. (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - 1961. (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - 1962. (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - 1963. (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - 1964. (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - 1965. (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - 1967-68. (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - 1969. (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - 1970-71. (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - 1972-73. (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - 1975. (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - 1976-79. (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - 1980s. (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - n.d. (Box 26, Folder 14)
- Articles. (Box 26, Folder 15-17)
- Articles. (Box 27, Folder 1)
- UCLA student term papers. (Box 27, Folder 2-6)
- Photographs and negatives. (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Articles by Cesare Marchetti. (Box 27, Folder 8)
- International Secretariat for Research on the History of Agricultural Implements. (Box 27, Folder 9)
- Technics and civilization, by Lewis Mumford. (Box 27, Folder 10)